So what is synthesis, and why is it so important,
particularly at the end of problem-solving efforts?
Synthesis is taking everything you've done as part of
the problem-solving process and getting to the “so what”.
Why does this matter to me, or to the organisation?
Often we see, particularly at the end
of large, complex, long projects,
so much analysis has been done that there is a desire — a bias —
to share all the data and information, to show how much work was done.
What you really want to do at this stage
is to stop and think:
what is the “so what” from all of this?
Absolutely critical. And why does it matter?
Then focus on that synthesis.
Now, it's important to understand there's a difference
between summary and synthesis.
A summary is often a more concise version
of the facts of that analysis.
The synthesis, though, is at a higher level:
it is thinking about what the takeaway is —
what to do with it, and what the “so what”
from that analysis is.
Let me give you an example. The other day,
my brother and I were planning to meet for dinner.
As I sat in the restaurant waiting for him, I got a very long
text message. He told me his meeting ran late,
he forgot his phone at the office and had to go back for it,
and he just missed the train.
That was a pretty good summary
of the events that had occurred to him.
What is the synthesis?
“I'm going to be late for dinner.”
So as you think about summary versus synthesis:
the synthesis is the insight we are getting to,
whereas the summary is the concise re-articulation
of all the facts that support that synthesis.